Okay, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Today's דף daf is מג, mem gimmel,
43. And we pick up with the bottom of very last line
of מב עמוד ב. mem bet amud bet. Okay, so this is
again with משוח מלחמה, meshuch milchama, the כהן kohein telling the people
you're going to go to battle, you know, you have God behind
you, you they, you know, they have the strength of flesh and
bone, you have God behind you. ואתם אי אתם כן, ve'atem ee
atem kein, and you are not like they. So it says, you
know, you have השם אלוקיכם הוא ההולך עמכם. Hashem elokeichem hu haholeich
imachem. Hashem is with you.
So you're going... so the גמרא Gemara says וכל כך למה, vechol
kach lama, what's all of this about? Now what do you mean
what's all this about? It gives them courage. So רש״י Rashi says,
if you look at רש״י, Rashi, וכל כך למה אומר להם ומה
היא הבטחה זו שהבטיחם כי השם אלוקיכם ההולך. ולמה כי השם אלוקיכם
עמכם, ומה היא הליכה זו, דמשמע הולך ממש. vechol kach lama omeir
lahem u'mah hi havtacha hazo shehivtiacham ki Hashem elokeichem haholeich. Velamar ki
Hashem elokeichem imachem, u'mah hi halicha zo, demashma holeich mamash.
So רש״י Rashi says the question is not why the statement, but
what's the emphasis of God is walking with you, is going with
you, not just is with you. מפני שהשם וכל כינויו מונחים בארון.
mipnei sheHashem vechol kinuyav munachim ba'aron.
Because you have actually God's name and all of the different forms
of God's name present in the ארון. aron. So therefore it is
actually... which is interesting, because in the ארון aron really was the...
was the לוחות, luchot, I mean I guess maybe it's also the
ספר תורה sefer Torah at the end of דברים, Devarim, right, לקוח
את ספר התורה הזה ושמתם אתו מצד ארון ברית השם אלוקיכם, likoach
et sefer hatorah hazot vesamtem oto betzad aron brit Hashem elokeichem, right,
because the לוחות luchot doesn't have all of the forms of God's
names, but anyway, you have God, so it's not just the abstract
sense of God is with you, but actually the physical thing that
represents God's presence is going with you. The ארון aron is taken
into battle. Interesting question, right, about whether they would actually take the
ארון aron out of like the, you know, בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash,
and would they take it with them into battle? There are certain
theories that there was a separate ארון aron that they would take
with... to battle, which wasn't the same ארון aron that was in
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash or in the משכן. Mishkan. Anyway, so
וכן הוא אומר, וישלח אותם משה אלף למטה לצבא, אותם ואת פינחס
בן אלעזר הכהן לצבא וכלי הקודש וחצצרות התרועה בידו vechein hu omeir,
vayishlach otam Moshe elef lamateh latzava, otam ve'et Pinechas ben Elazar hakohein
latzava uchelei hakodesh vechatzotzrot hateruah beyado is the פסוק. pasuk. So אותם...
otam... so it says אותם, otam, he sent them into war.
This is against מדין. Midian. אלו סנהדרין. eilu Sanhedrin.
So it was they were going like with the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, which
might have to do with the role also of the סנהדרין Sanhedrin
in declaring a מלחמת מצווה milchemet mitzvah or מלחמת... milchemet... so that's
the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. Or פינחס Pinechas זה משוח מלחמה. zeh meshuch milchama.
So there was a כהן, kohein, so that represents the משוח מלחמה.
meshuch milchama. וכלי הקודש זה ארון ולוחות. uchelei hakodesh zeh aron veluchot.
The
holy vessels, and that we are identifying as the
ארון aron and the לוחות, luchot, that becomes the paradigm of the
ארון aron leading them, going with them into war. שבו... shebo...
and לוחות luchot that were in the ארון. aron. וחצצרות התרועה vechatzotzrot
hateruah and the trumpets of blast, אלו שופרות. eilu shofrot. Interesting, it
takes the word וחצצרות vechatzotzrot and makes it into שופרות, shofrot, which
חצצרות chatzotzrot are the, you know, the manufactured חצצרות chatzotzrot out of
metal, the שופרות shofrot are the ones out of an animal's horn,
but there's another גמרא Gemara that actually says that the word for
חצצרות chatzotzrot became in later Hebrew, the word got reversed in terms
of what their meaning are. That שופר shofar meant חצצרות chatzotzrot and
חצצרות chatzotzrot meant שופר, shofar, so maybe that's why it's doing this
translation here.
בחצוצרות שופר בקשה לגבי חצוצרות? bichatzotzrot shofar bekesheh legabei chatzotzrot?
No no no, not in the תנ״ך. Tanakh. In the time of
the גמרא, Gemara, that those names got reversed.
So if you look at the שאילתות She'iltot by the מצווה mitzvah
of תקיעת שופר, tekiat shofar, he says דמיחייבין דבי ישראל למיתקע בחצוצרא.
demichayvin d'bei Yisrael lemitka bechatzotzra. Okay, so the...
so in the time of the גמרא, Gemara, the גמרא Gemara says
that those names got reversed, so maybe that's why it's doing the
translation here.
ומהמשמעת חצוצרא זו חצצרות. u'mimeshmechat chatzotzra zu chatzotzrot. Okay, but it's just
giving it that the current term for it is שופרות. shofrot.
Which is funny they've reversed back and... I understand, I understand.
Well, it has to do with the fact that Aramaic is no
longer our vernacular. Okay, תנא, tana, לא חנם הלך פינחס למלחמה. lo
chinam holeich Pinechas lamilchama.
It wasn't for naught that פינחס Pinechas went to war, meaning he
wasn't just the משוח מלחמה, meshuch milchama, there was something very appropriate
about him leading them to war against the מדינים. Midianim. אלא ליפרע
דין אבי אמו. ella lipara din avi imo.
To avenge or the, you know, to pay back the judgment for
his father's... his mother's father. שנאמר, shene'emar, what does that mean?
והמדנים מכרו אתו אל מצרים. vehamidanim machru oto el Mitzrayim.
So this was the war against the מדינים, Midianim, and we see
the מדנים, Midanim, which are assumed to be the same here as
the מדינים, Midianim, sold יוסף Yosef into מצרים, Mitzrayim, so we are
thinking that פינחס Pinechas descends from יוסף Yosef as Michael points out,
it cannot just be from יוסף Yosef because he's a כהן, kohein,
but that's why it says אבי אמו, avi imo,
his grandfather on his mother's side was from יוסף Yosef and therefore
he's taking... he's paying them back for having sold יוסף Yosef into
Egypt. למימרא, lemaymra, says the גמרא, Gemara, דפינחס מיוסף אתי? d'Pinechas miYosef
ati? You're saying פינחס Pinechas is a descendant of יוסף? Yosef? והא
כתיב, veha ksiv, אלעזר בן אהרן לקח לו מבנות פוטיאל לו לאשה,
ותלד לו את פינחס. Elazar ben Aharon lakach lo mibenot Puti'el lo
le'isha, vateled lo et Pinechas.
And פינחס Pinechas is the daughter of אהרן Aharon and this woman
who is from... on the daughters of פוטיאל. Putiel. So that's פנחס'ס
Pinchas's sort of, you know,
who he's descended from on his mother's side. So who is this
פוטיאל? Putiel? So the גמרא Gemara says מאי לאו דאתי מיתרו? mai
lav d'ati miYitro? So we have a classic explanation of what פוטיאל
Putiel means, which means that יתרו Yitro that פנחס'ס Pinchas's mother, אלעזר'ס
Elazar's wife, is somehow descendant of יתרו. Yitro. שפיטם עגלים לעבודה זרה
shepitem agalim l'avoda zara that he fattened calves for עבודה זרה. avoda
zara.
That's the language of פוטי אל, Puti El, like to fatten for
God, but not for lowercase g, for the gods. Okay, so you
see that he's not a descendant of יוסף, Yosef, he's a descendant
on his other side from יתרו. Yitro. So the גמרא Gemara says
לא מיוסף, lo miYosef, no we'll have the word פוטיאל Putiel mean
a יוסף Yosef descendant. שפיטפט ביצרו shepitpet b'yitzro that he sort of,
you know, disregarded his lust and his desire and was able to
conquer over it. So the גמרא Gemara says והלא, vahalo, what do
you mean? It's so funny, it's asking questions from like a traditional
מסורה mesorah or אגדתא aggadata about who יתרו Yitro was and who
he was descendant from, right? So it's not really challenging from a
פסוק pasuk but it's just פנחס Pinchas but it's just sounding from
like almost self-referential from its own understanding of who פנחס Pinchas was.
והלא שבטים מבזים אותו, vahalo shevatim mevazim oto, but the tribes would,
you know, denigrate him,
and they would say פנחס Pinchas when he went and he slew
זמרי Zimri and they said ראיתם בן פוטי זה? re'item ben Puti
zeh? Do you see this descendant of פוטי Puti שפיטם אבי אמו
עגלים לעבודה זרה? shepitem avi imo agalim l'avoda zara?
His grandfather fattened calves for עבודה זרה. avoda zara. Who is this
outsider? והרג נשיא מישראל. veharag nesi miYisrael. He has the temerity to
slay a leader of ישראל, Yisrael, like one of the leaders of
the tribes? And so that's a classic aggadic understanding of what happened
after פנחס Pinchas slew זמרי. Zimri. So you see that we really,
it's not just a מחלוקת, machloket, we really at a deep level
believe that he's descendant from יתרו, Yitro, so you can't just discard
that מדרש. midrash. So the גמרא Gemara says fine, who says he
has to be a descendant only from one line of lineage? He
has two lines of lineage even on his mother's side. אלא אי
אבוה דאמה מיוסף אמה דאמה מיתרו.
ella ee avuha d'immeh
miYosef immeh d'immeh miYitro. Fine, so who does his mother come from?
Either his his his grandfather, his mother's father, is יוסף Yosef and
his mother's descends from יוסף Yosef and his mother's mother descends from
יתרו. Yitro. Or the opposite. אבוה דאמה מיתרו אמה דאמה מיוסף. avuha
d'immeh miYitro immeh d'immeh miYosef. Or his mother's mother is from
יוסף Yosef and his mother's and his his his mother's father is
from יתרו. Yitro. So fine, on his mother's side he comes both
from יוסף Yosef and יתרו. Yitro. דייקא נמי דכתיב מבנות פוטיאל. dayka
nami dektiv mibnot Putiel.
It says פוטיאל, Putiel, it doesn't say פוטאל Putel or something like
that. תרי משמע. trei mashma. שמע מינה. shma mina. So there are
two lines of descent here and therefore he comes both from יוסף
Yosef and from יתרו. Yitro. So you have the tribes mocking him
or deriding him and at the same time you also have the
appropriateness of him seeking the vengeance against the מדינים. Midyanim. Yes.
So so in some way they're actually exacting נקמה, nekama, just by
going to war against them.
What are you talking about?
He's not fighting, is he?
Well, he's a oh, that's an interesting question.
Can a כהן Kohen like is he allowed to be in the
army and kill people?
Yeah, in theory, I mean there's
actually, um, לכתחילה? lechatchila? Yeah, yeah, yeah, about כהן Kohen and טומאת
כהנים tumat Kohanim in terms of the איסור issur of becoming טמא.
tameh.
Yeah, it's an interesting question.
Especially those days it's not like okay you shoot something you know
and you
don't
even see them, you're actually like literally causing a מת met and
then you come in contact and it's proximity.
Right, yeah, it's an interesting question. I'll have to look into that.
That's a good question. I'll have to get back to you about
like how much you know even in this גמרא'ס Gemara's context, I
mean obviously normally, you know, the לויים Leviyim would not go to
war,
but how much even in this context like you know, you don't
you don't imagine like the chaplain of the army he actually he
doesn't take up arms, so how much is he like but you
know nevertheless, I mean the role that he plays in terms of,
you know, giving them courage and direction and spiritual or whatever. But
yeah, but yeah, but it's a good question. It's a good question.
Right, yeah, even in those times they wrote a תשובה teshuva about
a כהן Kohen in the army? Yeah, I don't know, I don't
know. I'll I'll take a look. It's a good question. Okay, so
let's take a look at the next משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so there
we have that the you know that the משוח מלחמה meshuach milchama
says do not be fearful, God is going with you. And then
we turn to the next פסוק. pasuk. ודיברו השוטרים אל העם. vedibru
hashotrim el ha'am. Now the שוטרים, shotrim, the officers speak to the
people and they say לאמר laymor מי האיש אשר בנה בית חדש
ולא חנכו ילך וישוב לביתו, mi ha'ish asher bana bayit chadash velo
chanacho yelech veyashov leveito, right? Who built a new house, who built
a vineyard, who married a woman and did not, you know, and
has not been a year yet or betrothed a woman, to go
back. Okay, so now we're going to say who's included in these
categories. אחד הבונה בית התבן בית הבקר בית העצים.
echad haboneh beit hateven beit
habakar beit ha'etzim.
It doesn't have to be a house that you live in, it
could even be a house, a garage, right? A place for storing,
a good analogy, a place for storing you know a straw or
for or for cows, a barn, or a place for storing wood.
Some place that is like it's got a roof over it, a
tent, a shed. Right, so בית אוצר. beit otzar. or any storage
facility, it doesn't have to be an actual house. And it doesn't,
you don't even have to be the one who built it. אחד
הבונה ואחד הלוקח ואחד היורש, Echad HaBoneh Ve'Echad HaLoke'ach Ve'Echad HaYoresh, whether
you built it or purchased it or even just inherited. ואחד שניתן
לו במתנה Ve'echad shenitan lo bematanah
or even if it was given to you as a gift? Okay,
so very broad category. ומי האיש אשר נטע כרם ולא חללו, Umi
ha'ish asher nata kerem velo chilolo, who planted a vineyard and was
not מחלל mechalel it? Now,
the normal rabbinic interpretation of חללו chilolo is because we know that
it's talking about it did not spend four years with it, wait
till the fourth year when you do נטע רבעי, neta revai, you
know, כרם רבעי, kerem revai, the fourth year and you can be
מחלל, mechalel, you can transfer the value to money and bring the
money to ירושלים Yerushalayim and spend the money there in ירושלים Yerushalayim
on food rather than bring the actual fruit to it, which gives
you four years from the time of planting a vineyard, which is
quite a lot,
a large amount of time. I think some of the classic, some
of the like more modern biblical commentators, I think it might even
be in the אבן עזרא Ibn Ezra if I'm not mistaken, says
anyway that it means that you did not
like, like מחלל, mechallel, like did not, you know, like they do
a circle dance, what's those called,
the מחולות? mecholot? Right. So means that it's a certain way of
like לא חנכו, lo chanacho, like you didn't like, you know,
inaugurated it, right, you did not, so maybe it was whatever the
time was, maybe it was after a year, whoever, whatever it was,
but there was some type of an event of קודש הלולים, kodesh
hillulim, you know, הלולים hillulim or something, there's a whole play on
that about anyway, but that it means that there was not some
type of an inauguration of it. So it does not mean like
four years and כרם רבעי, kerem revai, but that's the way the
גמרא Gemara understands it, that is what it's referring to.
I think it's funny, I think it's תניא, Tanya,
there's one guy standing there. I know, I know. I know and
then you say, somebody told me, somebody told me that there was
a whole, that there was a whole like in the Yiddish theater
there was like a play like this or whatever, that you know
the כהן גדול kohen gadol gets up and he says okay who
built a house and whatever and like you know some five people
leave and like you know whatever like 10 people leave, 15 people
leave. Then it says who's afraid of the עבירות שבידו? aveirot she'beyado?
Everybody. There's two old guys with beards left. And one guy says
like אני מכבד אותך ani mechabed otcha with the first shot, no
no אני מכבד אותך ani mechabed otcha with the first
shot.
Anyway, alright so,
alright so anyway, consecrated. Anyway, so it could be read like you
know did not plant a vineyard and like dedicated it, consecrated it,
similar to like חנכו chanacho by the בית. bayit. But anyway, but
חז"ל Chazal read it means like you had four years, so that's
a lot of time.
Four years, on the fourth year when it became relevant you get
to do it, but the first three years you may...
correct, right? I don't think so, I think basically it's until it's
actually ready to be eaten.
Okay, so
אחד הנוטע כרם ואחד הנוטע חמישה אילני מאכל. Echad hanotei'a kerem ve'echad
hanotei'a chamisha ilanei ma'achal. So similar to before, it wasn't only limited
to a house, it's whether it's a vineyard or whether it's five
fruit trees because of standard vineyard has five, like a minimum-sized vineyard
for other הלכות halakhot has basically like you know five plantings. So
by analogy here it's five fruit trees, same as five vines for
a vineyard. ואפילו מחמישה מינים, Ve'afillu mechamisha minim, even if it's some
five different species, not even the same species.
אחד הנוטע ואחד המבריך ואחד המרכיב ואחד הלוקח ואחד היורש ואחד שניתן
לו במתנה. Echad hanotei'a ve'echad hamavrich ve'echad hamarkiv ve'echad haloke'ach ve'echad hayoresh
ve'echad shenitan lo bematanah. So not only if you plant, but whether
you plant or whether you
מבריך mavrich is basically you
extend
the vine or the root or whatever, the branch underground and it
grows up in another place. מרכיב Markiv is to actually do grafting.
And so a) it's not only the building, it's... I mean it's
not only the planting, it's other ways of you know of physically
causing growth, right? But also like the בית, bayit, it's not only
building it, it's not only doing something physical to it, it's even
just taking possession of it. Or you purchased or you inherited or
it was given to you in a gift. Okay, so that's the
כרם. kerem. ומי האיש אשר ארש אשה, Umi ha'ish asher eiras isha,
who betrothed a woman but has not yet done the נישואין nisu'in
ולא לקחה. velo lekacha. אחד המארס את הבתולה, Echad ha'me'ares et ha'betulah,
so whether it is a בתולה, betulah, ואחד המארס את האלמנה, ve'echad
ha'me'ares et ha'almanah, a woman who's never been married before or a
widow, אפילו שומרת יבם, afillu shomeret yavam, and even if it's not
an act of אירוסין, eirusin, even if it's just... so again what
sort of the structure is the same. First the sort of if
you would the object, here the woman is the object but is
you know it's not only a house it's even a barn, it's
not only a כרם, kerem, it's even a you know it's even
five trees, it's not only a בתולה, betulah, it's even an אלמנה.
almanah. And then it's the act of connecting to it, whether you
built it or whether you inherited, whether you planted it or whether
you inherited or purchased, whether you did the אירוסין eirusin or whether
the sort of the connection happened by itself. So she's a שומרת
יבם, shomeret yavam, you know this is a this is a brother's,
a brother's wife. ואפילו שמע שמת אחיו במלחמה, ve'afillu shama shemeit achiv
bamilchamah, even if you heard that your brother died in the war.
even if you heard that your brother died in war, חוזר ובא
לו *chozer uva lo*, then you return as well because now you
have a מצוה *Mitzvah* of יבום *Yibum*. Okay, so presumably even if
you've gone to the battle, once your brother's once one brother dies,
all the brothers leave because now they're all שומרת יבם *Shomeret Yavam*,
assuming the guy left a widow behind.
All right, so ובא לו *uva lo*. כל אלו שומעין דברי כהן
Kohen מערכי המלחמה *Kol eileh shomin divrei kohen marchim hamilchama*, all of
these hear the words of the כהן Kohen *kohen* at the battle
front and וחוזרין *vechozrin*, and they go back.
Do they have to go back or could they?
No, take a listen, where how far חוזרין *chozrin* is. חוזרין *chozrin*
doesn't actually mean they go back home. It means that they return
from the front ומספקין מים ומזון ומתקנין את הדרכים *umsapkim mayim umazon
umtaknim es hadrachim*. But they're in but they're in national service. They
have to provide, but they don't fight. Are they allowed to or
do they have to go back? I don't know, it's a good
question.
I'll have to look it up. Anyway, they provide food
and they're and they're with the corps of engineers, so they provide
support services and they're in the national service, but they're not actually
on the front. Okay, ואלו שאינם חוזרים *ve'eileh she'einam chozrim*, but the
following people do not go back. הבונה בית bayit, שער אכסדרה ומרפסת
*Haboneh bayis shaar achsadra umirpeses*, you built something, but it's not a
place, it's a place that's really just like an antechamber. It's a
gatehouse, it's not a place that anybody could live. Thank you, even
though a barn is for the cows, but in theory you could
live in a barn, it's a place for as opposed to this,
which is just made for like passing through or like a porch.
הנוטע ארבעה אילני מאכל *Hanotea arba ilanei maachal*, if it wasn't five
fruit trees, but there's only four fruit trees, וחמשה אילני סרק *vachamisha
ilanei srak*, or even if it was five, but if they were
not fruit trees, they were
basically barren trees of a species that did not bear fruit. המחזיר
גרושתו *Hamachazir gerushaso*, or if a man remarries his divorced wife because
then it's not a new wife to him. אלמנה לכהן גדול גרושה
וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט *Almanah l'kohen gadol gerusha vachaluza l'kohen hedyot*, or if
it's a betrothal, but it is forbidden. It's violating a prohibition, an
אלמנה *almanah* for a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol *kohen gadol*, even just
a positive מצוה *mitzvah*, or a גרושה *gerusha* for a normal כהן
Kohen *kohen*. ממזרת ונתינה לישראל *Mamzeres unsinah l'yisrael*, or in case of
a ממזר *mamzer* and a ישראל *Yisrael*, if it's a forbidden type
of בת ישראל לממזר ולנתין *bas yisrael l'mamzer ulenasin*, either one of
them, doesn't matter if it's the man or the woman. Anyway, if
it's a forbidden type of a union, then you would not be
חוזר *chozer*.
Well, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* I think is going to ask that.
The גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, very good, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will ask
that. לא היה חוזר *Lo hayah chozer*. רבי יהודה אומר אף הבונה
בית על מכונו לא היה חוזר *Rabbi Yehuda omer af haboneh bayis
al mechono lo hayah chozer*. Even if you rebuilt a house on
its foundation, it's similar to the idea of somewhat if you if
you excuse the analogy of המחזיר גרושתו *Hamachazir gerushaso*, if there's something
that is to basically restoring an old situation and not completely new.
Of course, if the house has been falling apart for like a
hundred years and you knock it down and rebuild it on its
foundation, it seems like it's pretty new to me. But anyway, that's
what he would say. And that's what he said. Okay. רבי אליעזר
אומר אף הבונה בית לבנים בשרון *Rabbi Eliezer omer af haboneh bayis
beis
leveinim baSharon*, even you know if you build a brick house in
the שרון *Sharon*. What does it we say at יום כיפור *Yom
Kippur*? על אנשי השרון היה אומר יהי רצון שלא יהיו בתיהם קבריהם
*Al anshei haSharon hayah omer yehi ratzon shelo yehi battehem kivreihem*. Right,
so anyway, it's very right, it's very unstable. What about the מכונו
*mechono*?
ושבנאו במדה ראשונה *v'sheh-bano b'middah rishonah*. Meaning, it's not like you expanded
it or made it nicer, you just
did it exactly the way it was. I understand, but nevertheless, if
you have a house that's been falling apart for a hundred years
and you knock it down and you rebuild it based on the
old specs, it's still a pretty new house, right?
But yes, שרון *Sharon* periodically gets major earthquakes that do a lot
of damage.
But yes, רש״י *Rashi* does say it's based on the same
on the same plan, but nevertheless, it could it certainly, if it's
been falling apart and you completely rebuild it to the old specs,
it's still pretty new, but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says at least
anyway according to רבי יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* it is not. Okay. And
רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says this brick house in the שרון *Sharon*
also is very unstable and it's not really you would not be
חוזר *chozer*. ואלו שאין זזים ממקומם *Ve'eileh she'ein zazim mimkomam*, so on
the one hand you have people that don't go back, that don't
return, that they stay at the front. Then you have the people
that leave the front, but they provide support services. And then you
have the third group of people that they don't even go to
the front and they just stay at home and they don't even
provide any support services. Okay, so they just get totally off. What
who are they? בנה בית וחנכו נטע nata כרם kerem. וחללו *Banah
bayis venachano natah kerem vechillilo*, now that's funny, it's against I think
what you would have thought פשט pshat? *peshat* of the פסוקים psukim
*pesukim* is. You actually did inaugurate your house or the fourth year
of the כרם kerem. *kerem*. You would think great, now you don't
have any unfinished business, now you should go to the front. הנושא
ארוסתו *Hanosei arusaso*, or somebody who actually did not just betroth the
woman, but actually married her. והכונס את יבמתו *Vehakoness es yevamto*, or
by analogy, did the act of יבום *yibum* with his sister-in-law, שנאמר
נקי יהיה לביתו Levayso שנה אחת *shene'emar naki yiheyeh l'veiso shanah achas*.
So this is if it's ארש אשה ולא לקחה *erash isha v'lo
lakacha*, you return. And then the other פסוק *pasuk* says that if
a man who actually married a woman, not just did אירוסין erusin
*erusin*, נקי לא יצא בצבא ולא יעבר עליו לכל דבר נקי לביתו
שנה אחת Naki levayso shana achas. ושמח את אשתו Vesimach es ishto
אשר לקח Asher lakach *naki lo yeitzei batzava v'lo yaavor alav l'chol
davar naki l'veiso shanah achas vesimach es ishto asher lakach*. That after
he does the ליקוחין *likuchin*, after they are actually married, he gets
a year off. Okay. So it's interesting. Again I think when you
read the פסוקים psukim. אירסתי אשה ולא לקחה Arashti isha velo lakacha
the sense you get is oh if you have unfinished business you
go back. But if you actually finish the business as it was
you had the נישואין nissu'in then you're going to go to war.
But actually what the גמרא gemara says is the opposite. If you
have the unfinished business but it's not yet fully actualized that type
of a thing then you are providing support services. You don't go
on the front but you don't go all the way back home.
You stay behind and you provide support services. Once it has been
actualized אירסתי אשה ולקחה Arashti isha velakacha then you get off for
the whole year. And the same way that's true by the case
of the אירוסין and the נישואין nissu'in it's true by all the
cases the משנה Mishna saying by the house and by the vineyard.
That once it's been actualized actually it's not like you go to
war it's actually then you get actually a whole year to actually
just be free from the army service. So it says let's just
read it נקי לביתו שנה אחת. לביתו זה ביתו ze beiso for
the house the house that he was חנכו chanacho he actually got
to the level of חנכו. chanacho. יהיה זה כרמו. Yihiye ze karmo.
How you get that? I don't know it. Okay. ושמח את אשתו
זו אשתו. zo ishto. אשר asher לקח להביא את יבמתו. lehavi es
yevamto. אין מספיקין מים ומזון ואין מתקנין את הדרכים. Ein maspikin mayim
umazon ve'ein metaknin es hadrachim. They are totally off from any support
services from any army service altogether.
מלחמת הרשות Milchemes hareshus right? Right.
כן זו מלחמת הרשות Ken zo milchemes hareshus right that's worth emphasizing
and all of this is מלחמת הרשות milchemes hareshus going outside the
land of Israel correct. מלחמת מצוה Milchemes mitzvah everybody goes to war
that is correct. Okay but anyway very interesting. It's certainly true that
that's in terms of the case of
marrying a woman but it would not have been the sense you
would have gotten just reading the פסוקים of אירסתי אשה ולא לקחה
Arashti isha velo lakacha and what the משנה Mishna here does is
it broadens it to all three of those cases. So once actually
that thing has been completed it's actually a year off a fully
off of army service.
Okay I'm sure the Israeli army actually doesn't do that.
תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan our rabbis taught: ודברו השוטרים. vedibru hashotrim. Okay
the the officers will speak and this is about מי האיש אשר
בנה בית חדש mi ha'ish asher bana bayis chadash etc.
יכול Yachol דברים של עצמן devarim shel atzman maybe their own words.
Now what do you mean their own words? It sounded like they
just had to read a script. It was only before that we
gave the כהן Kohen גדול a little few some words off the
script about גליות galiyos etc. So what's going to become clear in
a minute is it doesn't just mean whether it's their own words
or the words that's provided for them in the
תורה Torah but are they repeating what the משוח מלחמה meshuch milchama
speaking or are they sort of
speaking on their own? So are they presenting themselves as the speakers
or are they just or is the משוח מלחמה meshuch milchama still
the speaker and they're just now communicating and amplifying right basically like
the role of a תנא tanna or the role of an אמורא.
amora. So maybe they're speaking on their own? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar
ויספו השוטרים veyasfu hashotrim which is the part that we haven't spoken
about in this משנה Mishna which is when the תורה Torah says
and then they will go and do more and they will once
again speak and they'll say about הירא ורך הלבב hayarei verach halevav
who is fearful. So הרי דברים של עצמן harei devarim shel atzman
there they're speaking on their own.
אמור? Emor? מה אני מקיים Ma ani mekayem ודברו השוטרים? vedibru hashotrim?
בדברי משוח מלחמה הכתוב מדבר. Bedivrei meshuch milchama haksav medaber. That's where
the משוח מלחמה meshuch milchama speaks and they amplify. כיצד? Keitzad? כהן
מדבר ושוטר משמיע. Kohen medaber veshoter mashmia. Exactly like the role of
the תנא tanna or the role of the אמורא. amora. So כהן
Kohen speaks and they amplify. I mean it's a huge troop so
they go around into all of their various sections and repeat it.
Okay now תני חדא כהן מדבר ושוטר משמיע. tani chada kohen medaber
veshoter mashmia. We have one ברייתא braisa that says the כהן Kohen
speaks and the שוטרים shotrim are the ones that amplify and make
it that people can hear. ותני אידך Vesani idach with another ברייתא
braisa כהן מדבר וכהן משמיע. kohen medaber vekohen mashmia. The כהן Kohen
does the speaking all on his own. ותני אידך שוטר מדבר ושוטר
משמיע. Vesani idach shoter medaber veshoter mashmia. The שוטר shoter does the
speaking all on his own or the שוטרים. shotrim. So how do
you reconcile this? אמר אביי Amar Abaye הכי קאמר. hachi ka'amar. There's
how is this possible because there are three different roles.
מניגש עד ודברו Minigash ad vedibru from when it says the כהן
Kohen draws near until it says and the שוטרים shotrim speak which
is the speech we mentioned before which is do not fear God
is going with you. That's כהן מדבר וכהן משמיע. kohen medaber vekohen
mashmia. That's all straight from the כהן Kohen. which by the way
makes sense because that's all about having courage and God is with
you so you want the כהן to be the one that's doing
that all by himself. מודברו עד ויספו Mivedibru ad veyasfu from the
first section where it says ודברו השוטרים vedibru hashotrim where it talks
about the house and the wife and the vineyard that's כהן מדבר
ושוטר משמיע. kohen medaber veshoter mashmia. The כהן speaks and the שוטר
shoter is the one who amplifies.
מויספו ואילך Meveyasfu va'eilach from when it says and then they add
to this and they say so that and that's about the person
who is fearful that's שוטר מדבר ושוטר משמיע. shoter medaber veshoter mashmia.
That's all the שוטר. shoter. Now why exactly besides the fact that
okay it has different verbs it has different players but what exactly
is the significance of that? Not a hundred percent clear to me.
Again why the כהן would be the one to do the whole
first part by itself I understand. You want to say God is
with you don't be afraid you have God's presence. You want to
be hearing that straight from the כהן. I think that probably the
reason the thing about being fearful is said only by the שוטרים
shotrim
is because we're going to see later. Later that the שוטרים *Shotrim*
actually, I think as you probably are aware, that armies have very
harsh consequences
for desertion, right? That a deserter is put to death because all
you need is one person to desert and then other people desert
and whatever, you can't have that. So people have to realize. So
the שוטרים *Shotrim* were given the authority that if anybody basically tried
to desert, they would just kill them on the spot. So the
שוטרים *Shotrim* on one hand are saying מי האיש הירא ורך הלבב
*Mi ha'ish hayare ve'rach halevav*, if you're afraid, leave now, we don't
want that fear to be demonstrating itself in battle, and they're going
to be the ones that are going to keep order in the
ranks during battle to make sure that people don't act on their
fear. So I think it makes a certain amount of sense that
they're the ones when it gets to that last section that are
doing it all on their own. So the first section is all
the כהן *Kohen*, the last section is all the שוטרים *Shotrim*, this
middle part about בנה בית חדש *bana bayit chadash* and ארש אשה
*eras isha* etc., that's some combination of the two. Okay, so now
the גמרא gemara *Gemara* continues. תנו רבנן Tanu rabanan. *Tanu Rabbanan*: מי
האיש אשר בנה בית חדש *Mi ha'ish asher bana bayit chadash*. So
it's not only building, it's even purchasing, it's even inheriting, it's not
only a house, it's even a barn, etc. Okay, תנו רבנן *Tanu
Rabbanan*: אשר בנה *Asher bana* אין לי אלא אשר בנה *ein li
ela asher bana*, I only know building. לקח וירש וניתן לו במתנה
מניין *lakach veyarash venitan lo bematanah minayin*? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar: *Talmud
lomar*: מי האיש אשר בנה *Mi ha'ish asher bana*. Okay, so somehow
אשר בנה *asher bana* is seen as an extra word to include
even these other forms of taking possession. בית *Bayit*. אין לי אלא
בית *Ein li ela bayit*. מניין לרבות בית התבן ובית הבקר ובית
העצים ובית האוצרות *Minayin lerabot beit hateven uveit habakar uveit ha'etzim uveit
ha'otzarot*? How do I know all these storage houses? תלמוד לומר Talmud
lomar: *Talmud lomar*: אשר בנה מכל מקום *asher bana mikol makom*. Because
before you get to the word בית *bayit*, רש״י *Rashi* says again,
don't ask me because the other way would have been bad grammar,
but רש״י *Rashi* says it could have said אשר בית בנה *asher
bayit bana*. And it says אשר בנה בית *asher bana bayit*, so
you get to the word בנה *bana* before you get to the
word בית *bayit*, so בנה *bana* anything similar to a בית *bayit*,
even if it's not exactly a בית *bayit*. Okay, so יכול שאני
מרבה אף הבונה בית שער אכסדרה ומרפסת *yachol she'ani marbeh af haboneh
beit sha'ar achsadra umirpeset*? Maybe I would include even some type of
a gatehouse, some place that's not really made for, nobody can sleep
in or live in, it's just made for passing through, a porch
or something of that nature. תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar: בית *Talmud lomar:
Bayit*. It has to be similar to a בית *bayit*. מה בית
הראוי לדירה *Mah bayit haraui ledirah* that if you wanted to you
could live in it, אף כל הראוי לדירה *af kol haraui ledirah*.
These places you couldn't live in even if you wanted to. רבי
אליעזר בן יעקב אומר *Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov omer*: לא בית כמשמעו
kemashma'o *lo, bayit kemashmao*. He's the one that defends the פשט pshat
*pshat* of the פסוקים *psukim*. I'm sorry, it's got to be a
real house. If you build a barn, it doesn't count. ולא חנכו
chanacho, *Velo chanacho*. Why do you have to have the personal pronoun
ולא חנכו *velo chanacho* was not מחנך *mechanech* it? Why didn't it
just say ולא חנך chanach *velo chanach* wasn't מחנך *mechanech*, and the
it would have been implicit? פרט לגזלן *Prat legazlan*. It has to
be something that you would have been entitled to be מחנך *mechanech*,
to inaugurate, as opposed to, or maybe it's somehow yours, and to
exclude a גזלן gazlin? *gazlan* where you would not, even if you
took possession of it through theft, obviously that would not get you
off from the army. So the גמרא gemara *Gemara* says: לימא דלא
כרבי יוסי הגלילי *leima d'lo k'Rabbi Yosi haGelili*? This sounds not like
רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yosi haGelili*. רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר ורך הלבב
זו המתיירא מעבירות שבידו *Rabbi Yosi haGelili omer: Verach halevav zu hamityare
me'aveirot shebeyado*. There you go, Dov. So Dov was asking about why
you needed to exclude somebody who engaged in a forbidden act of
marriage, that that's not the good case of ארש אשה *eras isha*,
since רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yosi haGelili* says that somebody who's fearful
is not fearful just out of normal reasons, but fearful because they
have sinned. So anybody who has sinned basically and hasn't done תשובה
*teshuvah* would have to leave.
So why do you need to exclude somebody who stole a house?
For רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi Yosi haGelili*, that would be in the
category of somebody who sinned and is fearful of העבירות שבידו *ha'aveirot
shebeyado*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: אפילו תימא רבי יוסי הגלילי *afilu
teima Rabbi Yosi haGelili*. No, it could be רבי יוסי הגלילי *Rabbi
Yosi haGelili*. כגון דעבד תשובה ויהב דמי *kegon de'avad teshuvah veyahav damei*.
He did תשובה *teshuvah* and not only did תשובה *teshuvah*, what good,
it's still עבירה שבידו *aveirah shebeyado* if he hasn't made restitution. Okay,
so he did תשובה *teshuvah* and he made restitution, so it's no
longer עבירה שבידו *aveirah shebeyado*, he's dealt with it. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says one minute: אי הכי *ei hachi*, if he paid for
it, הוי ליה לוקח *havei lei loke'ach*. So now he's a legitimate
purchaser. Now he's entitled to keep it. He paid for it.
Let him go back from the מלחמה milchamah. *milchamah*. It says no:
כיון דמעיקרא בתורת גזילה אתא לידיה לא *keivan demeyikara betorat gezeilah ata
lidei, lo*. No, nevertheless, it was, it came to him through theft
and therefore that's not included in the פרשה *parsha* of אשר בנה
בית חדש *asher bana bayit chadash*. תקנת השבים
*Takanat hashavim*. Oh, that's a good point, if we do this, won't
we prevent the, because for תקנת השבים *takanat hashavim* we should let
him go back. Exactly, שבים *shavim* from the מלחמה *milchamah*, yeah. Exactly,
שבים *shavim* from the מלחמה *milchamah*, yeah.
So ולא חנכו *velo
chanacho*
means...
so I don't know if there's, it's a good question like is
there an official type of a thing that's ולא חנכו *velo chanacho*?
Does it mean to begin to live in it?
Sure, look, you know, you have a housewarming party, right?
Yeah, no, I know, but I don't know, it's a good question
like I don't know if it's officially defined. I mean, right, like
when do you start counting the year? If you've got a year,
like when do you start counting it, right? Does the punch list
have to be complete?
What?
I can tell, let me see what the, how the רמב"ם brings
it down.
הלכות בונה, Hilchot Boneh, הלכות בונה, Hilchot Boneh, הלכות רועיה, Hilchot Rovaya,
הלכות קובע. Hilchot Koveia.
Yeah, he just says חנכו, he just says like the גמרא.
I don't know. I'd have to look if there's a better definition
of what that exact moment of חנכה chanaka is. Yes.
Associate the sin with the sin. So those other people who might
be fearful they didn't sin, they might feel that they look as
if they sinned, if they go back because
they're afraid.
Yeah, so I think that, I think we'll get to it. I
mean I think the fact that you can like because you wouldn't
necessarily differentiate the two groups of why people were going because of
fear of sin,
so if you didn't want to be associated with you know one
group or whatever, like if everybody who's afraid for different reasons, either
you're just סתם stam afraid of war or you're afraid of sins,
goes back at the same time, right you wouldn't necessarily have to
right subdivide them. Oh you also didn't oh well that's the other
thing also that it's like on the honor system. You don't have
to bring any proof that you get the exemption. I'm serious! Like
whoever fine, I'm leaving. Okay.
So, right it wasn't done in waves, it was like done you
know all at once, then everyone left at the same time, because
otherwise you'd be able to know who was going back for sins,
so alright
let's take a look. Fine. We're going to get to the last
category tomorrow.
Okay. So, ומי אשר נטע כרם Umi asher nata kerem who planted
a vineyard. תנו רבנן. אשר נטע. Asher nata. אין לי אלא נטע.
Ein li ela nata. I only know about planting. לקח וירש וניתן
לו במתנה
מנין? Lakach veyarash venitan lo bematana minayin? תלמוד לומר: ומי האיש אשר
נטע כרם. Umi ha'ish asher nata kerem. So again the אשר is
seen as extra. Now כרם. kerem אין לי אלא כרם. Ein li
ela kerem. מנין לרבות חמשה אילני מאכל ואפילו משאר מינין? Minayin lerabot
chamisha ilanei ma'achal ve'afilu mishar minin? How do I know any types
of fruit trees even if they're not from vines? And again the
assumption is five is somewhat representative of a כרם. kerem. תלמוד לומר:
אשר נטע. Asher nata. So the
אשר נטע Asher nata comes before the word כרם kerem. to allow
for נטע nata to have a broader meaning. יכול שאני מרבה הנוטע
ארבע אילני מאכל וחמשה אילני סרק? Yachol she'ani marba hanotea arba ilanei
ma'achal vechamisha ilanei srak? Maybe even if they're not fruit-bearing trees or
they're only four? תלמוד לומר: כרם. Kerem It has to be like
a כרם. kerem. By the way, I wonder what happens if you
combine the two ריבויים? ribuyim? What if you buy five trees? Right?
What if you buy a barn? Do you have to have at
least one of those words to be פשט? pshat? You have to
either build a barn or buy a house, like what if you
buy a barn? What if you buy five fruit trees? Anyway, okay.
So the גמרא says רבי אליעזר בן יעקב אומר כרם כמשמעו. Rabbi
Eliezer ben Yaakov omer kerem kemashma'o. No, again he's defending פשט pshat
of the פסוקים. כרם kerem. means like it sounds. לא חללו
ולא חללו. Lo chilalo velo chilalo. Oh okay, let me say a
word by the way about the word כמשמעו kemashma'o which is I
think it's always interesting, difference between כמשמעו kemashma'o and פשוטו. pshuto.
You know, if you think about it כמשמעו kemashma'o, means as it
sounds. It means literally כמשמעו, kemashma'o. as it sounds, it means a
כרם. kerem, So how is it different than פשט? pshat. Okay, when
the גמרא says like פשוטו כמשמעו. pshuto kemashma'o. Right? So I think
and actually Dr. Fishbane you can correct me if there's more scholarship
I'm not aware of, but I think scholars understand that actually the
word פשט Pshat does not mean in the way it's used in
חז"ל, Chazal, does not mean somehow like the simple meaning or the
way it would have been understood by people of the time, the
things that we mean by פשט. pshat I think that that's the
word like כמשמעו. kemashma'o? פשט pshat. means like the official meaning, like
the authorized meaning. So the פשט of it, right?
What? פשטיה דקרא pshatiah dekra would be the contextual sense.
The contextual sense? But what's פשוטו? pshuto?
Oh when you stretch it out,
oh when you stretch it out and look at it in a
larger context, and what's כמשמעו? kemashma'o Just like in the immediate local
sense? Oh that's interesting. So פשוטו pshuto means in the larger context
and כמשמעו means, aha. But פשט כמשמעו pshat kemashma'o is I think
normally what we mean when we say פשט. It's like what it
sounds like, it sounds like a בית, it sounds like כרם. kerem,
Okay. לא חללו ולא חללו. Lo chilalo velo chilalo. What's the לא
חללו lo chilalo where not מחלל mechallel it? פרט למבריך ומרכיב. Prat
lemavrich umarkiv. To exclude the case of somebody who does this like
you know using the shoot to grow somewhere else or somebody who
grafts it now.
What's going on there? First of all, how's that connected to חלל
chillel and לא חללו? lo chilalo? But also והא תנן אחד הנוטע
ואחד המבריך ואחד המרכיב, veha tnan echad hanotea ve'echad hamavrich ve'echad hamarkiv,
that it doesn't matter whether you planted or whether you did these
other types of things. Okay, so why should this matter?
And not only that, I mean why should that be worse than
if you planted? purchased it. Okay, so אמר רבי זירא אמר רב
חסדא לא קשיא כאן בהרכבת איסור כאן בהרכבת היתר. amar rabbi zeira
amar rav chisda lo kashya kan beharkavas isur kan beharkavas heter. So
no, what we're really excluding, similar to remember what we did before
about חנך and חנכה, chanachoh, we excluded the גזלן? So we're doing
something similar here to חילל chillel and חיללו, chillelo, and we're excluding
when you did this through doing an איסור. isur. And what type
of an איסור isur could you do? Well, if you're grafting, you
could do an איסור isur by כלאים. kilayim. Well, maybe okay, but
you could do כלאים. kilayim.
So the גמרא says, so that's the problem. So what we're doing
here is we're excluding a case when one has grafted באיסור. be-isur.
So the גמרא says okay, הרכבת היתר היכי דמי? harkavas heter heichi
dami? Now let's understand the case of הרכבה harkavah where you are
חייב chayav to I mean where you are allowed to go back,
the normal הרכבה harkavah of grafting.
אילימא ילדה בילדה, ileima yeladah be-yeladah, something that is within three years
onto something that is within three years, that's called ילדה, yeladah, a
young one, so it's still in the category of ערלה orlah and
it's still category of לא חיללו, lo chillelo, it's not yet the
fourth year. So תיפוק ליה דבמיהדר משום ילדה ראשונה. teipuk lei d'bamehadar
mishum yeladah rishonah. So why do you need to tell me that
the grafting exempts you? You're exempt because you have the thing you
grafted it on that's in the first three years. אלא ילדה בזקנה.
ela yeladah be-zkeinah. No, what you did is you put a young
shoot into an older vine. So you own the old vine, that
would not exempt you, you took a shoot, you bought a shoot
off of your friend or whatever from his young vine and then
you grafted it onto your old vine. So now that you grafted
this shoot, it's like you have a new young vine and therefore
you are exempt from the war. That would be the case. So
the גמרא says והאמר רבי אבהו ילדה שסיבכה בזקנה בטלה ילדה בזקנה.
ve-ha-amar rabbi abahu yeladah she-sibchah be-zkeinah batlah yeladah be-zkeinah. If you have
a young, you know, vine that basically gets wrapped around and wrapped
into an old one, the halakhic status for ערלה orlah follows the
old tree, the primary thing that it's grafted onto defines whether it's
ערלה orlah or not. So if you graft a young vine onto
an old vine, it would take the status of the old vine
and it would not be ערלה. orlah. And presumably, if that's the
point of לא חיללו, lo chillelo, then this status is now an
old vine and it would not exempt you from מלחמה. ואין בה
דין ערלה. ve-ein bah din orlah. So אמר רבי ירמיה לעולם ילדה
בילדה. amar rabbi yirmiya le-olam yeladah be-yeladah. Fine, it's a young vine
on a young vine. So then why do you need to be
exempt from the graft, aren't you exempt from the existing vine? כגון
דנטעו להך קמייצא לסייג ולקורות. kegon d'nat'o lehach k'maisa li-syag u-le-kora. But
no, the young vine that's the base that you're grafting onto, that
was not planted for producing fruit. That was planted to serve as
like a boundary marker, like a gate essentially, like to you know
a wall between you and your neighbor's field or something, or you're
planting a tree and you want them for their beams, okay? You
don't want it for fruit. דתנן, de-tenan, there's fruit anyway, it bears
fruit but it's not חייב chayav in ערלה orlah because it's or
it's not חייב chayav in נטע רבעי neta revai because it's not
planted for the sake of the tree, okay?
So you get to eat the fruit with no problem.
Presumably, I mean, question about who's keeping you honest, but that's
רבי ירמיה, rabbi yirmiya, again a fine distinction. To have ערלה orlah
that's not שייך shayach to ערלה. orlah. This is רבי ירמיה? rabbi
yirmiya?
This is רבי אבהו? rabbi abahu?
No, אלא לעולם ילדה בזקנה.
ela le-olam yeladah
be-zkeinah.
רבי ירמיה. rabbi yirmiya. Okay, I see. Okay fine. Okay you're right.
Okay, דתנן הנוטע לסייג ולקורות, de-tenan ha-note'a li-syag u-le-kora, if somebody is
planting a tree to serve as essentially like a type of a
fence or for its beams, פטור מן הערלה. patur min ha-orlah. Okay,
you're exempt from ערלה. orlah. So therefore what happens? So the first
tree you planted or the vine you planted is actually not going
to get you out of the war because it doesn't have a
whole status of ערלה orlah to it. It's so funny how the
status of ערלה orlah defines if you get out of the war,
but that's how we're reading חיללו. chillelo. But now you graft on
it a young vine that you want to use for the fruit
and that actually now that has an ערלה, orlah, that new young
vine, and that actually does get you out of the war. Okay,
ומה ישנא ילדה בזקנה דבטלה. u-maishnah yeladah be-zkeinah d'batlah. One minute, but
if you graft a young vine on a three-year-old you know on
an older tree or whatever on an older vine, then it takes
totally on the status of the base of the older vine and
it's and it's exempt from ערלה. orlah. ומה ישנא ילדה בילדה u-maishnah
yeladah be-yeladah this case, where the base is a young tree or
a young vine but it's exempt from
ערלה, orlah, so לא בטלה, lo batlah, why don't we say that
the new grafted part, why did that retain its own status and
is חייב? chayav? Why doesn't it become incorporated into the base and
also be exempt? Does everybody understand the difference? Right? You've got your
three-year-old, if you've got your if you've got your here your old
tree, right? This is I don't know five years old, okay? And
you put on a new young shoot, we say that this becomes
like this, it becomes like a זקנה zkeinah and it's פטור patur
in ערלה, orlah, right? What? I know, but now what we said
is, yes, but now we're asking how is it different? Because now
what we said is is that oh, so here's the case where
you're not exempt because of the old thing but you want to
be exempt for the new thing. You've got a young you've got
a young tree, okay? That's two years old, okay? But this is
but you planted it לקורות. le-kora. So then... this is פטור patur
*patur*, right? It's פטור *patur* in ערלה orla. *orlah*. Okay, and now
you put in this new vine, right, and now we're going to
say and you want this for the fruit, so this is going
to be חייב *chayav* in ערלה orla. *orlah*, right? That's our case.
So you weren't exempt for this, you put this into it and
you're חייב *chayav* and now you're חייב *chayav* for ערלה orla, *orlah*
and therefore you get it back from the מלחמה *milchama*.
That's not Rabbi Yose's case, that's not his case, right?
No, it is, that is, that is, that's the answer. Now the
question is why is this חייב *chayav* in ערלה orla *orlah* and
this פטור *patur*? If in this case the young vine gets incorporated
into the old and is פטור *patur*, so this the new young
thing should be incorporated into the base and the same way the
base is פטור *patur*, this should be פטור *patur*.
Okay, but the mere fact that you're doing it is you're repurposing
it.
Well, no, you mean even the base? We're not assuming that, but
the גמרא *Gemara* is going to give a similar answer, that this
at least in potential could be חייב *chayav* in ערלה *orlah*, if
you chose to want to get the fruit or whatever off of
the base, it would be חייב *chayav* in ערלה *orlah*. This at
least has the potential of being חייב *chayav* in ערלה *orlah* because
it's young, that does not.
So the intention is not strong enough to actually change...
Well that's what Michael, Michael was suggesting that if you're doing this
maybe you're redefining the whole thing, which you could say, but the
גמרא *Gemara* isn't going to say that. So the גמרא *Gemara* says
okay
where were we?
ומאי שנא ילד בילד דלא בטלה *U-mai shenai yelad beyelad d'lo batla*?
So דלא בטלה *d'lo batla*, that when it's the young and the
young, even though the base is not חייב *chayav* in ערלה *orlah*,
the shoot is. So the גמרא *Gemara* says השתא אם ממלך עליה
לאו בת מהדר היא *Hashtam im mimlech aleih lav bas mahdar hi*.
So in the first case of the old one, if you changed
your mind, would it matter? You would never, you could never return
from the מלחמה *milchama* for this old part of the tree. Okay,
it's old, it's okay. הכא *Hacha* here, אם ממלך עליה בת מהדר
היא *im mimlech aleih bas mahdar hi*. But here if you decided
that you're going to use the base actually for fruit then it
would be חייב *chayav* in ערלה *orlah* and you would go back
from the מלחמה *milchama*. So in that way this thing which you
are using for fruit allows it to retain its fruit status because
that's a status that could be relevant even for the base.
בת מהדר *Bas mahdar* means that which causes, enables you to return
from the מלחמה *milchama*, yeah? Exactly.
So in that case if I had trees that are older but
for four years or for my fence and then I decided just
to start using them to get fruit, whether or not I go
back?
Right, it sounds like it, it sounds like when it says בת
מהדר *bas mahdar* that that would be a basis of returning from
the מלחמה *milchama*. Okay, הכא אם ממלך עליה בת מהדר היא *hacha
im mimlech aleih bas mahdar hi*, דהאי מעיקרא לפירא קאימי *d'hai meikara
l'peira kaimi*. Originally it was for fruit, so if you were to
turn it back into that purpose, that would be a basis of
going back. מידי דהוה אעלו מאליהן *Midei d'hava a-olu me'ei-lei-hen*, like fruit
that just popped up on its own that wasn't planted for any
purpose. דתנן *D'tnan*: עלו מאליהן חייבין בערלה *olu me'ei-lei-hen chayavin b'orlah*. Okay,
now of course that's not the world's best proof because then you
could say if it had no purpose it's different than having a
defined purpose and that you're able to redefine it. But yes, it
does sound from the גמרא *Gemara* that not only is the fact
that this in potential could have been חייב *chayav* allows the new
thing to have to be חייב *chayav*, to not be completely incorporated
into the old, because the status you're giving the new to some
degree was a potential status of the old, but it sounds like
just that would have changed the status of the old both for
ערלה *orlah* and for מלחמה *milchama*, which is a bit of a
חידוש *chiddush*. Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: ולוקמה
*v'lokma*. גמרא *Gemara* says wait, wait, okay so that's your answer. How
could you have a case of הרכבה *harkava* that, I mean the
reason that it said that it doesn't apply was a הרכבת איסור
*harkavat issur*. The case that you have הרכבה *harkava* that
you're חייב *chayav*, why not say it's talking about the כרם kerem?
של שני שותפין *kerem shel shenei shutfin*? Basically Michael has, you know,
a young vine that's חייב *chayav* in ערלה *orlah*. Michael is sent
out to the war and I basically say to Michael: Michael, you
know, I don't have a vine, but what I do have is
I went and I bought this shoot of a vine from somebody
else, let me graft it onto your vine and I will own,
maintain ownership, it'll be your vine that it's grafting on, but I'll
maintain ownership of the grafted part and I'll get the fruit and
then I'll also get out of the war. Okay? So that's a
case where because your base is a ילדה *yelada*, you know, it's
this still has a status of ילדה *yelada* and is חייב *chayav*
in ערלה *orlah*, and but I need this exemption because I don't
get the... because it's his vine that's the base. So I still
need my exemption.
If I sell you all my fruit, I don't get out of
the war, right? Correct. Okay, in these cases you have to show
up for roll call and they send you home.
And they don't send you home, you have to provide support services.
You can stay, okay, after lunch you have to...
right, you have to do שירות לאומי *sherut le'umi* still. Okay. ולוקמה
בכרם של שני שותפין *V'lokma b'kerem shel shenei shutfin*, דהאי הדר אדידיה
והאי הדר אדידיה *d'hai hadar adideih v'hai hadar adideih*. So אמר רב
פפא *Amar R' Pappa*: זאת אומרת *zo meres*, this teaches you, כרם
kerem של שני שותפין אין חוזרין עליו מעורכי המלחמה *kerem shel shenei
shutfin ein hozrin aleih mei-orkhei hamilchama*. No, if you don't have whole
ownership over it, you do not go back. go back from the
war, which is a little bit funny because it's one thing that
we have joint owner and nobody owns any distinct part. Right here,
if Michael owns the base and I own the shoot, really, in
that case Michael wouldn't go back if he allowed me to graft
my one, that's one thing to say I don't go back. So
it's a little funny, like when you ממש *mamash* are joint owners
you can understand that nobody has any distinctive ownership. Okay, so the
גמרא *Gemara* says ומאי שנא מחמישה אחים ומת אחד מהם במלחמה *u-mai
shna mikhamisha achim u-mes echad mehem bemilchama* we're going to see this
case, five brothers, one of them died in war, דכולם חוזרים *dikulam
chozrim* they all go back because any one of them might do
the מצוה *mitzvah* of יבום *yibbum*, and it's a case of ארש
אשה *erast isha*, so it's but they're not all doing the מצוה
*mitzvah* of יבום *yibbum*, so isn't that similar to a case of
שותפין *shutfin*? גמרא *Gemara* says no, actually it's different. התם כחד וחד
קרינן ביה אשתו *Hasam kochad vechad karinan bei ishto*, there any one
of them, whoever winds up doing the יבום *yibbum*, is it she
becomes solely his wife. Okay, so it's true, we don't know which
one is going to do it, the חיוב *chiyuv* is on all
of them, but the end result will be a, you know, a
distinctive relationship. הכא כחד וחד לא קרינן ביה כרמו *Hacha kochad vechad
lo karinan bei karmo*, here it's not כרמו *karmo*. Now it doesn't
say כרמו *karmo*, it says מי האיש אשר נטע nata. כרם kerem,
ילך ולא חללו ילך וישוב לביתו ואיש אחר יחללנו *mi ha'ish asher
nata kerem yelech ve'lo chililo yelech veyashuv leveito ve'ish acher yechalelenu*. So
it doesn't say כרמו *karmo*. But nevertheless, so it's not a דרשה
*drasha* on the פסוק *pasuk*, but the גמרא *Gemara*'s saying if it's
not a sense of distinctive ownership, you would not go back. But
again, the case by the vine I don't understand because it is
distinctive ownership. He totally owns, you know, the main base vine and
I totally own the shoot, so again, that's that's not a classic
case of שותפות *shutfus*, that's actually we own different pieces of the
same vine, so it's not clear to me why at least Michael
I think at least should get to go back. Yes.
Four brothers potentially marrying this one woman... right, compared to two people
sort of owning an olive tree. Exactly.
Okay, fine. As long as you understand what we're talking about. Okay.
Right.
Okay, so now the גמרא *Gemara* says like this,
different
types of potential...
looking at any
fruit-bearing
tree, not just the vine...
any fruit-bearing tree. Right. I've been giving the vine example, it's any
fruit-bearing tree. Okay. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak
amar*, okay, so that was one answer, that the case of exemption
of מבריך *mavrich* was a case of מבריך *mavrich* of איסור *issur*.
So now we're and then we dealt with what's the case of
מבריך *mavrich* of היתר *heter*. But now we're going to go back
to this problem, what's the case of מבריך *mavrich* that is exempt?
So one answer was מבריך *mavrich* of איסור *issur*. רב נחמן בר
יצחק אמר במבריך אילן בירק *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar bemavrich ilan
beyerek*. The case is oh, I'm sorry, I think he's still giving
the same answer about... yeah, yeah, I'm sorry, he's still giving the
same answer of what's a case of מבריך *mavrich* היתר *heter* that
you're חייב *chayav*. So you somehow
grafted a
branch onto some type of a vegetable. I don't know how it
would work. I mean, what vegetables are strong enough to or whatever,
able to receive a branch a grafting? But if you could, that
would be an example where it's considered to where where it doesn't
get incorporated into the base because the base is a vegetable, it's
not a tree, so it maintains its own status. And if you
grafted it, it would be חייב *chayav* in ערלה *orlah*, if you
grafted a young branch somehow onto some type of a vegetable plant.
I'm not sure if that's allowed...
yeah, I was wondering...
well, we'll take a look. It's a debate whether that's considered כלאים
*kilayim*, actually, interesting... with one's a vegetable and one's a fruit...
yeah, you would think that it would be even more of a
problem. But anyway, so דתנן *detnan*, so let's take a look. אילן
בירק *Ilan beyerek*. האי תנא הוא דתניא *Hai tanna hu detanya* המבריך
אילן בירק *hamavrich ilan beyerek* רבי שמעון בן גמליאל מתיר *Rabbi Shimon
ben Gamliel mattir* משום *mishum* רבי יהודה בן גמאש איש כפר עכו
*Rabbi Yehuda ben Gamash ish Kfar Akko* וחכמים אוסרים *vachachamim osrim* and
they forbid it. So it would be a case what would be
הרכבת היתר *harkavas heter* according to one opinion, and it would be
a case where it would maintain the status of the ילדה *yaldah*
because you wouldn't be exempt for the base because the base would
be vegetable, and it wouldn't get incorporated into the base, it would
maintain its own status and be חייב *chayav* in ערלה *orlah*. So
that would be another case of הרכבת היתר *harkavas heter*. Okay, now
the גמרא *Gemara* says like this. Okay, so all that was one
answer about when are you exempt for הרכבה *harkava*, הרכבת איסור *harkavas
issur*, and then we wanted to figure out what's the scenario of
הרכבת היתר *harkavas heter*. But now we're going to give another explanation
of when you're exempt for הרכבה *harkava*. כי אתא רב דימי אמר
רבי יוחנן Rav Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan *Ki ata Rav Dimi amar
Rabbi Yochanan*, no, הא מני *ha manni*, this ברייתא *braita* that says
הרכבה *harkava* you're exempt is רבי אליעזר בן יעקב היא *Rabbi Eliezer
ben Yaakov hi*.
So so it's has nothing to do with הרכבת איסור *harkavas issur*.
When the end of the ברייתא *braita* said you're exempt if you're
מרכיב *markiv*, that's רבי אליעזר בן יעקב *Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov* who
darshens the פסוק *pasuk* כשמועתו *kishmuto*. לא אמר רבי אליעזר בן יעקב
התם כרם kerem, כשמועתו *Lo amar Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov hasam kerem
kishmuto*, the same way he said כרם kerem *kerem* literally means a
כרם kerem, *kerem*, and it does not mean a like fruit trees,
so הכא נמי נטע כשמועתו *hacha nami nata kishmuto*, נוטע אין מבריך
ומרכיב לא *nota in, mavrich umarkiv lo*. So if you remember the
ברייתא *braita* that we were working off of, the ברייתא *braita* first
had how do you know fruit trees etc., so it says אשר
נטע *asher nata*, and רבי אליעזר בן יעקב *Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov*
said no, no, no, כרם kerem, כשמועתו *kerem kishmuto*, it has to
only be a vineyard. And then it says חילל חיללו *chillel chililo*
to exclude a case of מרכיב *markiv*. So he's saying is that
that's not דברי הכל *divrei hakol*. So that's רבי אלעזר בן יעקב,
Rebbe Elazar ben Yaakov the same way רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rebbe
Elazar ben Yaakov insists on literally a כרם, he also insists on
literally נטע and nothing other than נטע. Okay. כי אתא רב דימי
אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, Ki asa Rav Dimi
amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rebbe Elazar ben Yaakov, now that we're talking
about statements in the name of רבי אלעזר בן יעקב Rebbe Elazar
ben Yaakov, and רב דימי Rav Dimi in the name of רבי
יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, right, so now we're going to have a couple
of statements of רב דימי Rav Dimi אמר רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
in the name of רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, Rebbe Elazar ben Yaakov.
somewhat in the same area but not exactly on topic. Okay. ילדה
פחותה מטפח, Yalda p'chusa mi'tefach, if you have a young tree that
will never grow more than a טפח, tefach, okay, חייבת בערלה כל
שנותיה. chayava b'orla kol shenoseha. Right, so its entire life it's חייבת
בערלה, chayava b'orla, which I don't know what good the tree is
going to do you if you can never—if you have to be
ערלה. But the point is people will look at it and if
it's might be five years old, but they'll think it's a two-year-old
tree because it's so small, okay, and therefore you always have to
treat ערלה. Again, I don't know what good it will do you
then. דמיחזי כבת שתא, D'michzi k'vas shata, it looks like it's always
a one-year tree. והני מילי שתים כנגד שתים ואחת יוצא זנב, V'hani
mili shtayim k'neged shtayim v'achas yotzei zanav, but that's only if you
have just a small group of those trees and even if you
have five and five is normally like a כרם, okay, if it
looks like a, you know, and when is five considered to be
like a כרם? Yeah, that's the picture before, when you have it
like this, that's considered like the configuration of a כרם and when
we're treating trees to be like a כרם, we would say it's
in that configuration. So even though they're like a כרם, you would
still have to give ערלה, but, but אבל כולה כרם, aval kula
kerem, if you really have a whole כרם here, which again, guys,
he might be actually, here it's only a טפח. tefach. I keep
on saying trees, before I was saying vines, here's when I should
be saying vines, right? I mean, what type of tree is only
a טפח, tefach, but he presumably he means like a vine. There
are some? Okay. But even if it would be a vine, right,
if the vine would be, you know, very small as well. But
if you have something that's really fully an orchard or fully a
vineyard, even if it's of these very short
things—we're seeing
that now with apple trees, some people sometimes have a טפח? tefach?
A
three-inch—not a טפח. tefach.
Anyway, anyway, if you—I'm sorry, wait.
So when is it that you're חייב בערלה? chayav b'orla? When it's
a small collection of those.
Five of them?
Even if it's five but it's a small collection. But if you
have a full כרם, again, what exactly defines a full כרם, but
a full vineyard or a full orchard or whatever it is, more
than just a bare minimum, קלא אית ליה, kala is lei, then
everybody knows, 'Hey, did you hear about ראובן? Reuven? He's got this
really weird vineyard, all these things are little midget trees or whatever.'
So in that case you're פטור in ערלה because people know about
those realities. Okay, and we'll read one more line. כי אתא רב
דימי אמר רבי יוחנן משום רבי אלעזר בן יעקב, Ki asa Rav
Dimi amar Rabbi Yochanan mishum Rebbe Elazar ben Yaakov, again רב דימי
Rav Dimi, came from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, said in the name
of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan, in the name of רבי אלעזר בן
יעקב. Rebbe Elazar ben Yaakov. That's the only reason these are collected
is because of that tradition here of רב דימי, רבי יוחנן, רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב. מת תופס ארבע אמות לקריאת שמע, Meis tofes arba
amos l'krias shema, if you're within ארבע אמות arba amos of a
dead body, you don't say קריאת שמע, krias shema, דכתיב לועג לרש
חרף עשהו. d'chsiv lo'eg l'rash chereif oseihu. Okay,
that one who what do you call it, that mocks the poor
is blaspheming God. So you're mocking the מת meis that you're saying
שמע shema and the מת meis is not able to say שמע.
shema. Right, it applies to other things as well. Okay, so we'll
pick up.